[Applause]
hello everyone this is Frank defus and
welcome to holot talk the internet's
laser and holography talk show enjoyed
in over 42 countries throughout the
world and now here's this week's
[Music]
show hello hello is this Martin indeed
it is how are you Martin it's Frank
defus hey Frank I'm glad to hear from
you good how's everything going up there
okay real good real good I've been
looking forward to our conversation I
hope I have something interesting to
convey probably the best way to start
all this out having you talk a little
bit about your work up there
specifically I imagine this through
Photon and Photon 2 how long have you
been involved with uh students teaching
them about photonics and holography okay
first of all let me say that Tantasqua
Regional High School where I teach is
located in Sturbridge Massachusetts many
of the listeners may be familiar roughly
where that is it's in central
Massachusetts and the school serves five
towns surrounding Sturbridge and has
about 1,00 students it has both an
academic and a technical Division and my
program in photonics is officially
vested in the technical division or what
used to be called vocational division of
many high schools and uh however is
available also to academic students as a
science elective in the school and we'll
talk a little bit more about what the
classes and the courses are but broadly
speaking I got involved D in this uh
several years ago about 3 years ago when
the director of tentas was technical
school and the head of the science
department approached me while I was
still in Private Industry and indicated
that they had found some grant money and
would I be willing to help them
construct a high school level curriculum
in photonics MH it turned out that I had
already done a bit of that through my
involvement with project Photon which
some of the listeners may know as a
national science Foundation sponsored
effort uh through the New England Board
of higher education to develop curricula
for high school Educators in subjects
such as fiber optics and lasers and
light in general fiber fiber optics was
actually your your main background at
one it was yes my uh my my my work over
the last 25 years in industry has been
in Optical fibers optical fiber
materials and infrared uh Optical
materials
mhm and this led to you going into the
high school when you were asked to run
these programs that's correct I'm a uh I
can't say that I'm the youngest guy in
the world but this is one of these
opportunities that comes along once in a
lifetime to uh convey the uh experience
and knowledge that you have to the Next
Generation if you will and it's I must
admit the uh best career move I probably
have made I wish I had done it 15 years
ago to be honest now holography entails
is a small portion of this this whole
program I imagine there are a lot of
other activities that you have going on
centered around the field of photonics
are you preparing students for for
moving out into the workforce for
instance uh they're indoctrinated into
the realm of photonics through your high
school and perhaps maybe move on to a
four-year college or even a technical
college after they graduate from high
school we do the program is end doing
all of those things first of all we do
train students for the world of work in
the um a traditional technical school
sense uh for example I have students
right now interning at some of the local
fiber optic companies and they use the
training and the knowledge that they
pick up in the photonics courses that
they've taken through my program uh
simultaneously since academic students
can take this program on what we call
the college preparatory or honors level
they can move on to a two or a four-year
college program with uh at least
sufficient knowledge so that they are
familiar with broad photonic concepts
with broad Concepts in Optics and
Optical physics and so that they at
least know many of the buzz phrases and
basic principles my intent has never
been to try and graduate miniature
electrical engineers from this program
but to give students a leg up whether
they're going into the world of work or
to college I know that the area that
you're in is actually a hot bed for um
photonics high-tech education at the
four-year level but uh how are things
for uh High Technologies photonics uh in
particular with your technical colleges
community colleges we have an extremely
good program very close to us here I am
uh uh not too far away about 45 minutes
drive from Springfield Massachusetts and
Springfield Technical Community College
has an outstanding two-year program in
lasers and electrooptic Technology at
the same time um a lady named Professor
Judy Donley teaches at Three Rivers
Community College here in Connecticut
about 45 minutes south and she teaches a
similar program and indeed has done
quite a bit of work uh retraining folks
from um for example the electric boat
division of General Dynamics when there
were large layoffs down there in the
area of fiber optics and photonics M
what's the interest like with the
students interest level is very high I
guess it's I guess the honest answer is
you uh get out of it what you put in and
thanks to um some of the uh things that
you've had up on your website the
activities that you've conducted the
holography ETC uh we've been able to get
the students uh fairly fired up I think
uh you and I had communicated by email
and I mentioned to you the fact that uh
my original plan in holography was to do
it as
a excuse me uh say one week activity or
so and it's turned into a two or three
week adventure uh because of the
students enthusiasm and interest that's
wonderful are are are they following any
uh particular path in high school um
this isn't a technical high school this
is are these honor students the students
that I have are both uh let me let me
say this first of all they are 10th 11th
and 12th graders okay they are generally
on the college prep or honors level they
are both Technical and academic students
and let me be clear so that the
listeners understand what the nature of
this program is the photonics technology
program at Tantasqua consists of a
series of courses they are one semester
each that is a half year they meet for
84 minutes each day so the kids get a
lot of learning in that one semester M
the first course that they would take
would be entitled introduction to light
and lasers and that covers exactly what
you think it does basic photonics what
is light what is lasers how do they work
what are its applications and it is at
that point that I introduce holography
as a as a basic topic and the students
are taught how to make process create
and learn about reflection holography
yeah the second course that they take
the second semester is entitled
introduction to fiber optics and in that
course they learn about fiber optics
both telecommunications fiber and non-
Telecommunications applications of
fibers such as Imaging laser power
transmission sensors Etc and in that
course they gain both um theoretical and
practical knowledge they have to learn
how to put connectors on fiber they have
to learn how to polish fiber they have
to learn how to measure fiber the third
course in the series is entitled uh
geometric and physical Optics and in
that course we do more holography
transmission holography we also learn
about Optical instruments and the
behavior of lenses and various Optical
elements finally we have some open
courses in the sense that they uh teach
students about principles of engineering
we have a course entitled exactly that
principles of engineering so the um
curriculum is quite varied that gives
you a quick idea of the types of courses
we have what are some of the actual
experiments that they would conduct in
the classroom environment oh well for
example uh they have to do everything
from build and interpret a Michaelson
interferometer to understanding how a
supermarket scanner works to learning
how to do um Optical time domain
reflectometry measurements on fibers uh
they learn how to splice and cleave
fibers I am blessed in the sense that
local industry has been very kind to me
with donations of equipment and I have a
very nice Fusion splicer that the
students can use uh I have an otdr that
they can use they uh also get involved
with uh building simple Optical
instruments telescopes uh camera obscure
is an exciting project that they did
with some of the art departments in our
school so there gives you a flavor
that's an incredible Preparatory course
well uh we want to keep expanding it as
I as I mentioned a moment ago one of the
the things that we're trying to do is
tilt it even more into what you and I
would consider a pre-engineering
curriculum and tying together some of
the other departments that we are
fortunate enough to have in the high
school for example we have a very good
CAD program at the school and I want to
uh pull in some of that to give the
students some experience in Optical
design for example I got a copy of um of
Oslo in one of the uh the um uh Oslo
Optical design program and one of the
board members on the project Photon
group uh has offered to come in and
teach that to the students has the
perception to holography changed at all
have you noticed any change in
perception of the students that you have
more students coming in already knowing
what a hologram is the answer the answer
is no none of them know uh know what it
is they've heard the phrase and they
associate it for example with um an
image that they see on a credit card or
one of those little sticky things that
they may have gotten on a keychain but
they don't understand it in the uh
sophisticated sense I might make an
editorial comment at this point just to
give you a little more background I was
first introduced to this topic a long
long time ago I think you and I may be
parallel in age but back in the U uh
late uh 60s when I was getting my
undergraduate degree in physics at
Rochester Institute of Technology the uh
Professor that I had assigned me to uh
the project of making a hologram yeah
and uh that was uh at the time just
shortly after several years after the
leth and up patnik papers came out mhm I
remember struggling very diligently to
finally get a a hologram out and was
very proud of it and basically dropped
it after that I continued my interest in
Optics but didn't have the opportunity
to do it again until I came to this High
School yeah yeah I also noticed that on
the web when I did a search for any
papers that you may have published you
had uh some articles in Scientific
American over the years would you like
to uh tell the listeners a little about
those articles on optical fibers yes uh
one of my primary research areas
over time had been in infrared glasses
again I was fortunate enough it's one of
these situations where you're I guess in
your career where you're in the right
place at the right time after I took my
Physics degree undergraduate degree uh I
wasn't exactly sure what to do and my
adviser said well um why don't you think
about going to Catholic University in
Washington DC because uh they're working
on a new a new fangled area that might
have some potential I don't really know
but I'm not sure he says it's called
fiber optics and they're working on
glasses and material for low loss
telecommunications Optical fibers and
since you have an interest in Optics why
don't you go down there and look at the
program well I did and I signed up for
uh a PhD program in in Material Science
okay and that in turn led me into uh
research and development work on glasses
infrared materials hermetic coatings on
optical fibers all kinds of um what at
that time was very high-tech stuff and
turned out to be a very uh interesting
and uh intellectually stimulating career
and I've been fortun enough to publish
quite a large number of papers in the
area of glasses Optical materials and
their applications yeah there was
another article that I had a chance to
take a look at that was about a marine
creature that uh it was sort of like off
the beaten path for fiber optics but
they somehow tied it together yeah well
you know it's one of these things where
where uh where
you the only place my uh 15 minutes of
fame is never up is here at home with my
wife and kids uh the I got a call one
evening from a reporter for Science
magazine and he had heard that I
supposedly knew something about fiber
optics and did I have any comment on a
new uh creature that had been discovered
that had these naturally occurring
fibers on them that guided light
apparently to the internal structure of
this animal wow and uh did I know
anything about that and I had to admit I
didn't my knowledge of uh biology is
matched only by my knowledge of sport so
uh the reporter and I talked a while and
I wound up giving him sort of a a crash
course in fiber optics which was really
the only way I could help him and that's
how the article came out yeah am I corre
correct in what I read that the
efficiency of the transfer light through
the spines or whatever it is of this
creature was actually more efficient
than what we were producing in the lab
uh I don't think I I don't recall that
being true I think it was a remember
this was a a very short section of fiber
and uh or a very short filament that's
on these animals and it's very difficult
to make uh a measurement of an extremely
low absorption coefficient over such a
short distance in the in the animal I
don't think that was true Frank no okay
all right um where do you plan to go
with your program and um where do you
see it in the future well boost clearly
our enrollment within tan task where
that's been uh a a difficult task
because some kids shy away from the
program they feel it might be too
complicated too
mathematical um too technical for them
and to answer or assuage those concerns
we've gone out to actually other high
schools in the area to attract new
students and we've also done a lot more
publicity work inside the high school I
do a couple of uh training or teaching
days for all of our ninth grade students
now so that I'll hopefully get a new
crop of 10th graders coming into the
program uh the other thing that we would
like to do I mentioned earlier in the
conversation and that's uh build the
program up into uh to include more
pre-engineering type of activities we
would like to create a engineering
Academy within Tantasqua high school
that might have a an admission exam and
bring in a very high quality of student
that we could then uh train for uh
admission to a four-year engineering
school that would be fantastic the other
thing of course to do is to keep on uh
and this is this is my little pitch here
is to keep on knocking on doors and hope
that people will continue to be generous
with their Don ations of equipment and
uh Parts high schools aren't uh the
first ones in line when industry thinks
of giving stuff away if you know what I
mean yeah yeah
exactly what would you say your gender
breakdown
is class have about I have about uh
25% girls in my class depending on what
the course is to be honest it varies
between like 15 25% MH uh young ladies
uh I encourage very much because I feel
strongly that women absolutely need to
be better represented in the engineering
disciplines the engineering professions
we have had um again difficulty in
attracting them because they feel it's
going to be too difficult yeah yeah my
my daughter's actually going for a
graduate degree in electrical
engineering now she's working down lock
keed Martin and she's uh pretty much
alone as a female you know doing some of
the work that she's doing I I noticed
when I I ran some classes uh for
approximately 10 years at the Franklin
Institute in Philadelphia the lazier in
holography program and I know when I
started Ed out in the mid 80s that I
would have approximately maybe one
female student per 15 to 20 male
students and by the time I was wrapping
things up and moving on in the mid 90s
it it was pretty much what you're seeing
now maybe about 25% of the class yeah so
I I I guess things have stayed that way
for a while that's actually I guess an
improvement but I guess uh 50/50 would
be the optimal what what you would be
looking for I guess well I can give you
the the opposite side that qu to
encourage both you and the listeners a
little bit the other what we didn't talk
about is the other course that I teach
at tantas is both college preparatory
and honors physics and in those classes
I have honors physics at the moment I
have 24 students in there and of
them I'm doing a quick rough count in
the top of my head here uh at least 11
or 12 are female okay and uh when I did
a show of hands at the beginning of the
semester here uh of all those students
uh more than 34 of them wish to pursue a
degree uh further education in what you
and I would consider technology be that
medicine uh biology uh engineering
disciplines whatever is Sturbridge in an
urban area no it is not it's relatively
uh rural we are about uh 65 miles west
of uh Boston town of Sturbridge has a
population of about 8,000 has certainly
couldn't be considered a a suburb of
Boston anyway 65 miles yeah there there
are some very interesting prr that are
happening in rural areas compared to
Urban right now yeah yeah what type of
holograms have you been making do you
have a website that uh anyone can visit
where they could see some of the
students work shortly shortly uh we will
be um putting up a new tantas website
and I have uh uh written and taken care
of the whole uh set of pages for my
program uh at the moment the best I can
do for you is our um uh the little
newsletter that I sent to you that chos
okay Mees that we have taken and also
has some photographs of my holographic
setup and that is located at the uh New
England Board of Higher Education
website and the listeners may be
interested in going there it's uh
www uh
NE
b.org New England Board of higher
education I'll make sure that there's a
link that goes directly to that area of
the website uh for the listeners if they
want to uh click on that and go over and
visit after the uh after they're
finished listening to the interview I
should uh also I should also say you
asked about what kind we've been making
we have been making both reflection and
transmission Holograms and uh as as you
know I've had uh exceptionally good
success now with the small uh diode
laser unit that you uh uh Supply people
with worked out uh very well indeed uh
it's helped us out a great deal in the
sense that uh we had been working prior
to that with just low power Heeney gas
lasers and had also tried some work with
a higher power argon laser without much
success and the um accessibility to that
diode laser setup and and I should add
having the kids actually build the
little power supply with it themselves
was very satisfying and then getting the
Hologram out of it was a how shall we
call it a double shot oh thank you very
much I appreciate that where do you see
this technology going from an Educator's
Viewpoint and the fact that you're
involved with this industry as as deeply
as you're involved with it you know
there's always emails that are coming
through about you know I want to uh
project a hologram of an actor on a
stage and I'm sure you probably get tons
of emails about that as well yeah
exactly and quite honestly I don't as
you say you've have much more experience
in that area than I do and sometimes I
don't know those the answers to those
questions I do know that photonics is a
good career area but uh holography I
should make clear to the listeners I
view it uh as an exciting and very
interesting photonic educational tool
that I use with the kids in the
following sense they learn not only the
theory and uh the principles of
holography why does it work you can
teach them through that portion of the
course concepts of interference and
defraction and make it real to them but
the holography also then allows them to
do and develop practical Optical skills
after we do the theoretical part on the
Blackboard I take them into our
laboratory give them a empty Optical
table okay now you have to set up all of
your equipment in accordance with the
instructions that we've had go ahead and
do it shoot the
Holograms make the plates we're
fortunate that we have a nice dark room
at tantas afterwards they have to
develop the plates themselves so they
develop uh photographic processing
skills and they get very excited about
being able to uh see things happen there
and work in a dark room um I can assure
the listeners that it's sometimes tough
to keep a half dozen or 10 people under
control in a dark room but it does
happen um and then finally having the
finished product and and they get to
take something home and show to their
parents a nice uh White Light reflection
hologram of of exceptional quality yeah
that it's it's a very successful program
with with disadvantaged youth as well
because of the visual qualities of
things that they bring in make the
Holograms as well while we have you on
the line and we have other Educators
listening I i' I'd like to ask you a few
questions about
safety in the classroom yes precautions
you take as far as goggles chemicals
what type of processing are you using
with the Holograms we are using the uh
standard what I'll call um uh if I if I
may be so bold the intergraph chemicals
uh um jd2 developers uh and others uh
the kids do have to wear in the dark
room um goggles aprons and uh if they so
choose uh rubber gloves I found that uh
the majority of them don't seem to uh to
uh uh take too kindly to the um these
very hot and uncomfortable latex gloves
uh in the classroom in my photonics
corses the very first lesson that on day
one is laser safety and we spend um
actually two days on that M uh learning
about what uh a laser not only what what
a laser is but what it can do to you
shock hazards as well as eye hazards
they have to memorize and learn all of
the um uh uh standards the classes of
lasers and which are important and which
are perhaps not so important here in our
classroom in the classroom and in the
laboratory they do wear a safety glasses
especially of course when we bring out
the higher power argon laser
H isn't that something safety is a very
critical thing in the in the uh uh the
Educators uh uh that are listening uh uh
should be aware of that indeed on the
New England Board of Higher Education
website I posted uh our laser safety
rules and a tote sheet if you will or a
onepage description that the students in
effect have to memorize M and I rigidly
enforce a three strikes in your rout
rule if I see a laser beam traveling
around the room the first time uh you
get warned if it's above chest height
the second time you get worned more
sternally and the third time you're out
for the
day hey you know hey I know I know I've
been in I've been in the class so when
you wake up in the morning thinking that
how things are going to go and then you
have to throw that all out the window
and start from scratch Once you walk
through the door of the classroom that's
for sure that's right having said all of
that the students are are very cognizant
they are very respectful of the
equipment they realize that they are
that it's a privilege for them to be in
this course because they have access to
equipment that tons more expensive than
any other student in the school yeah
exactly that's I I had an opportunity to
see the equipment in your lab and uh it
looks like Newport research taable and
all of your magnetic mounts and posts
and yes yeah it's very nice stuff for
students to be working with yes we uh uh
we are very fortunate uh uh uh offs
which is the former Lucent division here
in Sturbridge which manufactures uh
Telecom optical fiber has donated quite
a bit of material to us and indeed uh
they are giving us right now A 4x10
Newport Optical table wow on with air
flotation and uh I intend to set that up
in my laboratory there and hopefully I
use that as a a larger workspace for
demos and holography definitely yeah if
you get a chance to go back to the Hol
World website I just opened up another
area for doing those little mini
holographic portraits that the students
might be interested in too cool okay
yeah it combines a 35mm photography with
the shooting a little eight slit uh
laser transmission master and then doing
your uh Master to reflection copy
transfer see that's exactly the kind of
thing I need Frank for for my senior
level guys that's the kind of thing that
that yes I will definitely do yeah I had
I had that up once before and it it got
a little at the time there were a lot of
other things going on and it got a
little frustrated trying to keep up with
uh all of the questions and everything
so at the time I didn't really have a
solution to it but this time around I
said well I'm going to put this back up
and this time I'm going to make a very
bold-faced note that you should already
have some experience working with
holography you know this is not a
project if this is your first hologram
this is what you should do so I think
that possibly
May eliminate things with that but check
that out the students may be interested
in doing uh little portraits as a
project maybe you get your school
superintendent uh made into a hologram
or something I know Bill Pew did that
down in Jacksonville Florida speaking of
which yeah what is it like to be a
teacher working in photonics and
holography as well do you network with
other Educators across the country or do
you feel rather
alone through project Photon uh I have
excellent opportunity to network with
people we have our own list serve and uh
I will forward that address to you if
you if you don't already have it and so
project Photon through Judy Donley at
Three Rivers Community College and Nick
Massa at stcc Springfield Technical
Community College um handle this for us
and we have in that pro project some 60
Educators already who are implementing
this Photon curriculum throughout uh the
North noreast and in some senses
throughout the United States okay you're
somehow involved with the electro Optics
Center that's just outside of Pittsburgh
Pennsylvania as well I you no I am not
no I am not I'm I'm aware of it but I
have no involvement with it no yeah I
Wendy Gilpin I believe uh who is one of
the directors out at that Center just
north of Pittsburgh is on one of the
advisory boards for Photon so I thought
maybe there was something yes thank you
very much my my mistake yes I have met
her I recognize the name absolutely yes
yes but I've I have had no formal
contact with them nor have I ever
visited there oh okay yeah it's a pretty
nice place well Martin we're closing in
on our 30 minutes is there anything that
I should have asked you that I didn't
ask you that you'd like to add to the
interview before we close out uh I'd
certainly like to extend you and any of
the listeners an open invitation to stop
by if you're in the Sturbridge
Massachusetts area I'm happy to show you
uh what I have what I do and uh if the
readers have or listeners have any
questions uh they can easily contact me
by email it's uh I think you'll probably
put it up at your address it's uh Drex
Sage uh M Tantasqua that's t n
TQ a.org
Tantasqua
tantas great name how far are you from
um Stewarts Connecticut where University
Yukon 45 minutes really yeah very close
by oh I wish I just dropped my daughter
off there um over the weekend well yeah
it's it's uh as a matter of fact it's
right up 84 we're we are at the
intersection roughly speaking of Route
84 and the Massachusetts Turnpike okay
well I'll contact you next time I have
to run up to Yukon great and uh maybe we
can get together and at least have a cup
of coffee or something let's do it okay
okay Martin I want to thank you very
much if you want to hold on the line
I'll thank the listeners for tuning in
and